Guide to the Ellison and Lottie Hildreth Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Ellison and Lottie Hildreth Papers
1886-1977
RG 15
Yale University Divinity School Library
6
(15 boxes)
The papers provide valuable documentation of the work of the American Baptist South China Mission, complementing the Foster Family papers and Campbell Family papers also located at Yale Divinity School Library. The Hildreths' experiences are representative of many American missionaries to China in the early part of this century. Substantive correspondence with family members and fellow missionaries documents their striving to reach the mission field, their initial impressions of China, family life in China, daily educational and evangelistic work, and the political unrest rampant in South China during their tenure. The intense anti-Christian movement in the mid 1920s is well documented. Ellison Hildreth served as a Baptist home missionary from 1910 until 1913. From 1913-1927, the Hildreths were American Baptist missionaries in South China. During a furlough from 1918-1919, Ellison Hildreth served with the YMCA in Siberia. From 1928-1949, he served as pastor of Federated Churches in Vermont and Connecticut.
Hildreth, Ellison, 1884-1962
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1882Jun 18 Lottie Rowe Lane born in Walpole, Massachusetts, daughter of Everett Lane and Carrie Wetherby Lane.
1884July 17 Ellison Story Hildreth born in Holyoke, Massachusetts, son of Judge John Hildreth and Kate Barker Story Hildreth. (Ellison was also known as "Bob", and in later life as E. Story.)
1905 LRL, B.A., Mt. Holyoke College. Following graduation, she taught school in New York and New Jersey.
1906 ESH, B.A., Amherst College.
1906-1907 ESH attended Colgate Rochester Seminary.
1909 ESH graduated from Union Theological Seminary, N.Y.
1909 Dec ESH became a Student Volunteer at the SVM convention in Rochester, N.Y.
1909-1910 ESH taught at Cedarcroft School, Pennsylvania.
1910-1913 ESH served as Baptist home missionary in Covelo, California.
1913Jun LRL and ESH married. Children: John Lane Hildreth and Alice Lane Hildreth.
1913-1927 American Baptist missionaries in South China. After two years of language study in Kakchieh, they were assigned to Chaochaofu. On return from furlough in 1920, ESH was in charge of the country work around Chaochaofu and in 1923 a few churches north of Swatow were added to his field.
1918-1919 ESH served with YMCA in Siberia.
1927 ESH attended seminary. Family unable to return to China because of poor health.
1928-1936 ESH pastor of Federated Church in Cabot, Vermont.
1936-1940 ESH pastor of Federated Church in South Royalston, Vermont.
1940-1949 ESH pastor of Federated Church of Christ, Brooklyn, Connecticut.
1962 Dec 17 ESH died.
1977 Nov 24 LLH died.
Scope and Contents
The Hildreth Papers provide valuable documentation of the work of the American Baptist South China mission, complementing the Foster Family Papers and Campbell Family Papers also located at YDSL. Ellison and Lottie Hildreth were well-educated and intelligent New Englanders whose experiences are representative of many American missionaries to China in the early part of this century.
Substantive correspondence with family members and fellow missionaries documents their striving to reach the mission field, their initial impressions of China, family life in China (including the death in infancy of their first two children), daily educational and evangelistic work. and the political unrest rampant in South China during their tenure. Extensive correspondence from Ellison to Lottie during the six years prior to their marriage deals primarily with events of daily life but provides glimpses of the difficulties encountered in coordinating family expectations with early plans to go to China. In letters from China to their parents, Ellison and Lottie give detailed descriptions of events and surroundings. In April of 1916. for example, Ellison wrote to his mother about the revolution taking place around them: "Swatow has gracefully gone to the rebels. The chief magistrate fled on board a Chinese warship and left the harbor. We hear that Chaoyang, Kityang, Unkung, Thenghai and Kaying have all sided with the rebels. That means that the power and the soldiers are all in the hands of the revolutionary party, and we can expect as good protection as we have had or better." (ESH to mother 1916 Apr 1 (Box 3, Folder 34))
During this period of unrest, Ellison and some fellow missionaries were involved in negotiations between warring factions. (A rubbing of the granite stone memorializing this involvement is in OVERSIZE material. Photograph and translation available in Box 11, Folder 148.)The intense anti-Christian movement in the mid 1920s is well documented. A letter from Ellison to William Ashmore and others dated 1925 Dec 28, for example, provides detailed description of anti-Christian demonstrations occurring at Christmas in Chaochaofu.
Substantive documentation of the situation in South China is also available following the Hildreths' final return to the U.S. in 1927 through letters of fellow missionaries, particularly those of Ben and Alice Baker, the Hildreth's American Baptist colleagues at Chaochaofu.
The Notes and Writings of Series II deal primarily with the China experiences of the Hildreths. Included are many notes for talks about China given after their return to the United States. Of particular interest among the writings about China collected by the Hildreths is a typescript document by Emanuel H. Giedt entitled "Early Mission History of the Swatow Region Brought Down to the Present for the American Baptist Mission" (1946).
The Personal Items and Memorabilia of Series III shed light on the context of the Hildreths' China years. Family background is provided through newspaper clippings and an autobiographical sketch of Ellison's early years. A notebook-diary from the China years details daily events. A few written musings of Lottie provide insight into her personal feelings and beliefs. Photographs of the Hildreths' surroundings and colleagues in China are well identified.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1902-1967
II. Notes and Writings, 1914-1966
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1886-1977
Missions -- China; Missions; Clergy; Educators; Missionaries; Hildreth, Ellison, 1884-1962; Hildreth, Lottie Lane, 1882-1977; American Baptist Foreign Mission Society; Young Men's Christian Associations of China
- Correspondence, 1902-1967; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided into the following categories:
  A. Family Correspondence
  1. Correspondence of Ellison Story Hildreth (to LLH, to/from parents)
  2. Correspondence of Lottie Lane Hildreth (to ESH, to/from parents)
  3. Correspondence of Ellison and Lottie Hildreth (to/from children, siblings, aunt)
  B. General Correspondence
  - Family Correspondence
    - Correspondence of Ellison Story Hildreth
      - ESH to Lottie Lane Hildreth, 1905-1908 May (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
      - ESH to Lottie Lane Hildreth, 1908 Jun-1918 (Box 2, Folder 13-24)
      - ESH to Lottie Lane Hildreth, from China and the United States, ca. 1919, 1927, ca. 1938, no date (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - ESH to Lottie Lane Hildreth, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 26-27)
      - ESH to John and Kate Barker Story Hildreth (parents), 1907-1924, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 28-37)
      - ESH from John and Kate Barker Story Hildreth (parents), 1910-1911, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - ESH to Carrie Lane (mother-in-law), 1915-1916, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence of Lottie Lane Hildreth
      - LLH to Ellison Story Hildreth, 1916-1940 (Box 4, Folder 40-42)
      - LLH to Carrie and Everett Lane (parents), 1905,1911-1915 Sep (Box 4, Folder 43-53)
      - LLH to Carrie and Everett Lane (parents), 1915 Oct-1938, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 54-67)
      - LLH to/from Kate Hildreth (parents-in-law), 1907-1937 (Box 6, Folder 68-70)
    - Correspondence of Ellison and Lottie Hildreth
      - ESH and LLH to/from Lucelia Wetherby (aunt of LLH), 1907-1922 (Box 6, Folder 71-73)
      - ESH and LLH to/from Fannie Hildreth (sister of ESH), 1914,1915,1938 (Box 6, Folder 74)
      - ESH and LLH to/from John (Jay) Hildreth (son), 1940-1965, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 75-77)
      - ESH and LLH to/from Alice Hildreth Ballou and family (daughter), 1940,1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 78)
      - ESH and LLH to/from siblings of LLH, 1902-1913 (Box 6, Folder 79-82)
      - ESH and LLH to/from siblings of LLH, 1914-1965, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 83-92)
  - General Correspondence
    - Adams, Mabel and ?, 1923,n.d. (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - Allen, Benjamin F., 2nd, 1904-1906 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - American Baptist Foreign Mission Society, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - Ashmore, William et al, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - Associate Mission Treasurers (See also: Lacey, Ethel), 1925-1938 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - Baker, Alice and Ben, 1922,1925-1938,n.d. (Box 7, Folder 95-100)
    - Bartholomew, Bob, 1912-1938, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 101)
    - Bolles, Charlton, 1907,1909, 1940,1944 (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - Boresfield, Lillie, 1926 (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - Brinstad, C.W., 1911 (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - Brown, Velva, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Buchelen, E.B., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Butler, E.S., 1916 (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Capen, 1915-1929 (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Chamberlin, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Cheng, S., 1940 (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Chwang, S., 1926-1928 (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Clark, Brooks, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - Edgar, Alice, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - Everham, M., 1927,1931 (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - Field, L.D., 1946 (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Franklin, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Fuller, A., 1926 (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Griesbach, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Giffen, Annie M., 1928-1951 (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - Haggard, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - Hallock, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - Hazen, Florence and William, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - Herrick, W.B., 1909 (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - Hobart, Kenneth and Waneta, 1931-1932 (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - Huggins, Alice M., 1934 (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - James, Douglas, 1927-1929 (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - James, Mary, 1925-1928, 1934,1945 (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Johnson, Enid, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Knowlton, N.H., 1905 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Lacey, E.L., 1926-1929 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Lyon, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Megladding, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Miller, E.C., 1923,1940 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Montgomery, Helen Barrett, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Mott, John R., 1910 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Northcott, Fannie, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Page, A.H., 1925 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Perley, T.C., 1909 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Petty, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Pitzipies, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Ross, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Satterlee, M., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Simpson, M., 1928 (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Smart, M, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Smith, E., 1931 (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Smith, Helen, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Smith, Hugh, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Terrell, William G., 1946 (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Towner, William K., 1914-1920 (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Traver, Edith, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Van Kirk, Ruth, 1920-1941, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Wallace, G.T., 1926 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Waters, M., 1930 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Wetherby, Harriette, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - Wickes, Fanny, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - Whitman, Elia, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - Worley, Prudence C., 1930 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - YMCA in Russia, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - First names only: A-R (Box 8, Folder 117)
    - Fragments: no names, 1945,n.d. (Box 8, Folder 118)
- Notes and Writings, 1914-1966; Series II
  A. By Ellison Story Hildreth
  B. By Lottie Lane Hildreth
  C. By ESH and LLH
  D. Miscellaneous writings about China
  The notes and writings are arranged chronologically within these categories.
  - By Ellison Story Hildreth
    - Thesis submitted to Rochester Theological Seminary: "The Present Apparent Conflict between Foreign and Nationalist Interests in China, with a Suggested Plan of Reconciliation", 1927 (Box 9, Folder 119)
    - Miscellaneous, 1925,n.d. (Box 9, Folder 120)
  - By Lottie Lane Hildreth
    - Re. China, 1914,1925-1940, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 121-124)
    - Miscellaneous, 1922-1966, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 125-127)
  - By ESH and LLH
    - "Kakchieh Weakly News", Vol. I, Nos. 1 and 2, 1914 (Box 9, Folder 128)
    - Skit, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 128)
  - Miscellaneous Writings About China
    - Including abstract of letter re. Baptist Central China Mission (1914) and "The Anti-Christian Movement in Swatow" (1926), 1914-1926 (Box 9, Folder 129)
    - Including "South China Diary" by Rev. A. S. Adams, 1928-1933 (Box 9, Folder 130)
    - Including "Early Mission History of the Swatow Region Brought Down to the Present for the American Baptist Mission" by Emanuel H. Giedt (1946), 1946-1953, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 131)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1886-1977; Series III
  A. Biographical documentation
  B. Printed Material
  C. Photographs
  1. Family
  2. Individual and group portraits
  3. Scenes
  4. Photograph album
  D. Postcards
  E. Artifacts
  - Biographical Documentation
    - ESH: autobiographical sketch of early years, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 132)
    - ESH and LLH: notebook, 1905-1927 (Box 10, Folder 133)
    - LLH: diary fragments and memorabilia, 1901-1928,n.d. (Box 10, Folder 134)
    - ESH and LLH: passports, certificate of registration, 1917-1927 (Box 10, Folder 135)
    - ESH and LLH: newspaper clippings and memorabilia, including re. extended families, 1886-1977,n.d. (Box 10, Folder 136)
    - ESH: Related to YMCA work in Siberia, 1918-1919 (Box 10, Folder 137)
    - ESH and LLH: personal financial records, 1898-1908 (Box 10, Folder 138)
    - ESH and LLH: personal financial records, 1923-1941 (Box 10, Folder 139)
  - Printed Material
    - Chinese calling cards, wedding invitation, etc., n.d. (Box 11, Folder 140)
    - Chinese New Testaments, hymnal, 1908,1931, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 141)
    - Unidentified Chinese language material, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 142)
  - Photographs
    - Family: (see also photo album below)
      - ESH and LLH, 1901-1942,n.d. (Box 11, Folder 143)
      - Children and grandchildren, 1921-1960,n.d. (Box 11, Folder 144)
      - Group photos, 1921-1925,n.d. (Box 11, Folder 145)
    - Individual and group portraits:
      - Primarily China missionaries and their children, 1913-1942, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 146)
      - Primarily Chinese, 1914-1940, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 147)
      - Ceremony dedicating monument honoring ESH, with explanations, c. 1918 (Box 11, Folder 148)
      - In Siberia, c. 1918-1919 (Box 11, Folder 149)
    - Scenes:
      - China - people and homes, 1914-1935, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 150)
      - China - miscellaneous, 1914-1929, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 151)
      - Japan, U.S., 1913-1964, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 152)
      - Photograph album, 1913-1922, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 153)
  - Postcards
    - China, U.S. (Box 13)
    - Europe (Box 14)
  - Artifacts
    - Including models of bound feet, straw slippers, small paintings (Box 15)
    - Oversize scrolls; Rubbing of granite memorial to ESH and others; Bamboo